<?xml version="1.0"?>
<law id="6762"><section_number>13.1-656</section_number><catch_line>Court-ordered meeting.</catch_line><history>1985, c. 522; 2005, c. 765; 2007, c. 165; 2010, c. 782.</history><order_by>00000000007030213.1</order_by><text><section prefix="A">The circuit court of the city or county where a corporation's principal office is located or, if none in the Commonwealth, where its registered office is located, may, after notice to the corporation, order a meeting of shareholders to be held:<section prefix="1">On petition of any shareholder of the corporation entitled to participate in an annual meeting if an annual meeting was not held or action by written consent in lieu thereof did not become effective within 15 months after its last annual meeting or, if there has been no annual meeting, the date of its incorporation; or</section><section prefix="2">On petition of a shareholder who signed a demand for a special meeting that satisfies the requirements of &#xA7; 13.1-655 if:<section prefix="a">Notice of the special meeting was not given within 30 days after the date the demand was delivered to the corporation's secretary; or</section><section prefix="b">The special meeting was not held in accordance with the notice.</section></section></section><section prefix="B">The court may fix the time and place of the meeting, determine the shares entitled to participate in the meeting, specify a record date or dates for determining shareholders entitled to notice of and to vote at the meeting, prescribe the form and content of the meeting notice, and enter other orders necessary to accomplish the purpose or purposes of the meeting.</section></text><refers_to><reference>13.1-655</reference></refers_to><referred_to_by><reference>13.1-655</reference><reference>13.1-657</reference><reference>13.1-658</reference></referred_to_by><structure><unit label="title" identifier="13.1" level="1">Corporations</unit><unit label="chapter" identifier="9" level="2">Virginia Stock Corporation Act</unit></structure></law>
