<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="18.2" level="1">Crimes and Offenses Generally</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="4" level="2">Crimes Against the Person</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="7" level="3">Criminal Sexual Assault</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>18.2-64.2</section_number>
	<catch_line>Carnal knowledge of a person detained or arrested by a law-enforcement officer or an inmate, parolee, probationer, juvenile detainee, pretrial defendant or posttrial offender, or confidential informant; penalty</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">An accused is guilty of carnal knowledge of a person detained or arrested by a law-enforcement officer or an inmate, parolee, probationer, juvenile detainee, or pretrial defendant or posttrial offender if he is a law-enforcement officer or an employee or contractual employee of, or a volunteer with, a state or local correctional facility or regional jail, the Department of Corrections, the Department of Juvenile Justice, a secure facility or detention home as defined in § 16.1-228, a state or local court services unit as defined in § 16.1-235, a local community-based probation services agency, or a pretrial services agency; is in a position of authority over the person detained or arrested by a law-enforcement officer, inmate, probationer, parolee, juvenile detainee, or pretrial defendant or posttrial offender; knows that the person detained or arrested by a law-enforcement officer, inmate, probationer, parolee, juvenile detainee, or pretrial defendant or posttrial offender is in the custody of a private, local, or state law-enforcement agency or under the jurisdiction of a state or local correctional facility or regional jail, the Department of Corrections, the Department of Juvenile Justice, a secure facility or detention home as defined in § 16.1-228, a state or local court services unit as defined in § 16.1-235, a local community-based probation services agency, or a pretrial services agency; and carnally knows, without the use of force, threat, or intimidation, (i) an inmate who has been committed to jail or convicted and sentenced to confinement in a state or local correctional facility or regional jail or (ii) a person detained or arrested by a law-enforcement officer, probationer, parolee, juvenile detainee, or pretrial defendant or posttrial offender in the custody of a private, local, or state law-enforcement agency or under the jurisdiction of the Department of Corrections, the Department of Juvenile Justice, a secure facility or detention home as defined in § 16.1-228, a state or local court services unit as defined in § 16.1-235, a local community-based probation services agency, a pretrial services agency, a local or regional jail for the purposes of imprisonment, a work program, or any other parole/probationary or pretrial services program or agency. Such offense is a Class 6 felony.
			An accused is guilty of carnal knowledge of a pretrial defendant or posttrial offender if he (a) is an owner or employee of the bail bond company that posted the pretrial defendant's or posttrial offender's bond; (b) has the authority to revoke the pretrial defendant's or posttrial offender's bond; and (c) carnally knows, without use of force, threat, or intimidation, a pretrial defendant or posttrial offender. Such offense is a Class 6 felony.
			An accused is guilty of carnal knowledge of a person serving as a confidential informant if he (1) is a law-enforcement officer; (2) knows that such person is serving as a confidential informant for the law-enforcement agency where such officer is employed; and (3) carnally knows, without use of force, threat, or intimidation, such confidential informant while such person is serving as a confidential informant or is expected to testify in a criminal case for which the confidential informant assisted the law-enforcement agency with its investigation. Such offense is a Class 6 felony.
		</section>
		<section prefix="B">For the purposes of this section:
			"Carnal knowledge" includes the acts of sexual intercourse, cunnilingus, fellatio, anilingus, anal intercourse, and animate or inanimate object sexual penetration.
			"Confidential informant" means any person, other than an employee of a law-enforcement agency, who engages in, or provides information about, criminal activity for the purpose of assisting a law-enforcement agency in investigating the criminal activity of another, in exchange for a benefit, the promise of a benefit, or the hope or expectation thereof.
			"Law-enforcement officer" means the same as that term is defined in § 9.1-101.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>1999, c. 294; 2000, c. 1040; 2001, c. 385; 2007, c. 133; 2013, c. 602; 2020, c. 479; 2020, Sp. Sess. I, cc. 26, 37; 2024, c. 592.</history>
</law>
