<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="18.2" level="1">Crimes and Offenses Generally</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="4" level="2">Crimes Against the Person</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="7" level="3">Criminal Sexual Assault</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>18.2-67.9:1</section_number>
	<catch_line>Use of a certified facility dog for testimony in a criminal proceeding</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">As used in this section, "certified facility dog" means a dog that (i) has completed training and been certified by a program accredited by Assistance Dogs International or by another assistance dog organization that is a member of an organization whose main purpose is to improve training, placement, and utilization of assistance dogs and (ii) is accompanied by a duly trained handler.</section>
		<section prefix="B">In any criminal proceeding, including preliminary hearings, the attorney for the Commonwealth or the defendant may apply for an order from the court allowing a certified facility dog to be present with a witness testifying before the court through in-person testimony or testimony televised by two-way closed-circuit television pursuant to § 18.2-67.9.</section>
		<section prefix="C">The court may enter an order authorizing a dog to accompany a witness while testifying at a hearing in accordance with subsection B if the court finds by a preponderance of the evidence that:</section>
		<section prefix="1">The dog to be used qualifies as a certified facility dog;</section>
		<section prefix="2">The use of a certified facility dog will aid the witness in providing his testimony; and</section>
		<section prefix="3">The presence and use of the certified facility dog will not interfere with or distract from the testimony or proceedings.</section>
		<section prefix="D">The party seeking such order shall apply for the order at least 14 days before the preliminary hearing, trial date, or other hearing to which the order is to apply.</section>
		<section prefix="E">The court may make such orders as necessary to preserve the fairness of the proceeding, including imposing restrictions on and instructing the jury regarding the presence of the certified facility dog during the proceedings.</section>
		<section prefix="F">Nothing contained in this section shall prevent the court from providing any other accommodations to a witness as provided by law.</section>
	</text>
	<history>2018, cc. 524, 699.</history>
</law>
