<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="2.2" level="1">Administration of Government</unit>
		<unit label="subtitle" identifier="I" level="2">Organization of State Government</unit>
		<unit label="part" identifier="A" level="3">Office of the Governor</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="1" level="4">Governor</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="1" level="5">General Provisions</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>2.2-107</section_number>
	<catch_line>Appointment of members of commissions, boards, and other collegial bodies; disclosure of resumes</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">Except as provided in the Constitution of Virginia, or where the manner of selection of members of boards and commissions is by election by the General Assembly, or as provided in Title 3.2 or § 54.1-901, but notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary, the Governor shall appoint all members of boards, commissions, councils or other collegial bodies created by the General Assembly in the executive branch of state government to terms of office as prescribed by law. Each member appointed pursuant to this section shall be subject to confirmation by the General Assembly and shall have the professional qualifications prescribed by law.</section>
		As part of the confirmation process for each gubernatorial appointee, the Secretary of the Commonwealth shall provide copies of the resume and statement of economic interests filed pursuant to § 2.2-3117 or 2.2-3118, as appropriate, to the chairs of the House of Delegates and Senate Committees on Privileges and Elections. For the purposes of this section and § 2.2-106, there shall be a joint subcommittee of the House of Delegates and Senate Committees on Privileges and Elections consisting of five members of the House Committee and three members of the Senate Committee appointed by the respective chairs of the committees to review the resumes and statements of economic interests of gubernatorial appointees. The members of the House of Delegates shall be appointed in accordance with the principles of proportional representation contained in the Rules of the House of Delegates. No appointment confirmed by the General Assembly shall be subject to challenge by reason of a failure to comply with the provisions of this paragraph pertaining to the confirmation process.
		<section prefix="B">The resumes and applications for appointment submitted by persons who are appointed by the Governor pursuant to this section shall be available to the public upon request.</section>
	</text>
	<history>1977, c. 447, § 2.1-42.1; 1978, c. 834; 2001, c. 844; 2005, cc. 803, 938; 2016, c. 729.</history>
</law>
