<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="2.2" level="1">Administration of Government</unit>
		<unit label="subtitle" identifier="I" level="2">Organization of State Government</unit>
		<unit label="part" identifier="C" level="3">State Agencies Related to the General Operation of Government</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="11" level="4">Department of General Services</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="7" level="5">Centralized Fleet Management</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>2.2-1176</section_number>
	<catch_line>Approval of purchase, lease, or contract rental of motor vehicle</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">No motor vehicle shall be purchased, leased, or subject to a contract rental with public funds by the Commonwealth or by any officer or employee on behalf of the Commonwealth without the prior written approval of the Director. No lease or contract rental shall be approved by the Director except upon demonstration that the cost of such lease or contract rental plus operating costs of the vehicle shall be less than comparable costs for a vehicle owned by the Commonwealth.
			Notwithstanding the provisions of this subsection, the Virginia Department of Transportation shall be exempted from the approval of purchase, lease, or contract rental of motor vehicles used directly in carrying out its maintenance, operations, and construction programs.
		</section>
		<section prefix="B">Notwithstanding other provisions of law, on or before January 1, 2012, the Director, in conjunction with the Secretary of Administration and the Secretary of Natural and Historic Resources, shall establish a plan providing for the replacement of state-owned or operated vehicles with vehicles that operate using natural gas, electricity, or other alternative fuels, to the greatest extent practicable, considering available infrastructure, the location and use of vehicles, capital and operating costs, and potential for fuel savings. The plan shall be submitted to the Governor for his review and approval. Once the plan is approved by the Governor, the Director shall implement the plan for the centralized fleet. All state agencies and institutions shall cooperate with the Director in developing and implementing the plan.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>1989, c. 479, § 33.1-403; 1997, c. 48; 1998, c. 329; 2001, cc. 815, 842, § 2.1-548.04; 2011, c. 813; 2021, Sp. Sess. I, c. 401.</history>
</law>
