<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="3.2" level="1">Agriculture, Animal Care, and Food</unit>
		<unit label="subtitle" identifier="I" level="2">General Provisions; Protection and Promotion of Agriculture</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="3">Governor's Agriculture and Forestry Industries Development Fund</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>3.2-312</section_number>
	<catch_line>Blue Catfish Processing, Flash Freezing, and Infrastructure Grant Program</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">The Governor may award grants from the Fund for the Blue Catfish Processing, Flash Freezing, and Infrastructure Grant Program to encourage efforts by political subdivisions to support the processing, flash freezing, and infrastructure of invasive blue catfish species.</section>
		<section prefix="B">Any funds awarded by the Governor pursuant to this section shall be awarded as reimbursable grants of no more than $250,000 per grant to political subdivisions to support blue catfish processing, flash freezing, and infrastructure projects.</section>
		<section prefix="C">The Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry shall develop guidelines for the Blue Catfish Processing, Flash Freezing, and Infrastructure Grant Program and administer the Blue Catfish Processing, Flash Freezing, and Infrastructure Grant Program on behalf of the Governor. Such guidelines shall (i) require that grants be awarded on a competitive basis, (ii) state the criteria the Governor will use in evaluating any grant application submitted pursuant to this section, and (iii) favor projects that create processing, flash freezing, and infrastructure capacity in proximity to small-scale blue catfish watermen.</section>
		<section prefix="D">The guidelines developed pursuant to subsection C may allow contributions to a project by certain specified entities, such as a nonprofit organization or charitable foundation.</section>
	</text>
	<history>2023, cc. 133, 134.</history>
</law>
