<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="10" level="3">Petroleum Storage Tank Fund</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.34:13</section_number>
	<catch_line>Levy of fee for Fund maintenance</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">In order to generate revenue for the Fund and to make the Fund available to owners and operators of underground storage tanks and to owners and operators of aboveground storage tanks, there shall be imposed a fee of one-fifth of one cent on each gallon of the following fuels sold and delivered or used in the Commonwealth: gasoline, aviation gasoline, diesel fuel (including dyed diesel fuel), blended fuel, and heating oil, as such terms are defined in § 58.1-2201; however, such fee shall not be imposed on (i) gasoline, aviation gasoline, diesel fuel (including dyed diesel fuel), blended fuel, and heating oil sold and delivered to the United States or its departments, agencies and instrumentalities for the exclusive use by the United States or its departments, agencies and instrumentalities, (ii) alternative fuel as defined in § 58.1-2201, or (iii) aviation jet fuel as defined in § 58.1-2201.
		</section>
		<section prefix="B">The fee shall be remitted to the Department of Motor Vehicles in the same manner and subject to the same provisions specified in Chapter 22 (§ 58.1-2200 et seq.) of Title 58.1, except § 58.1-2236 shall not apply.
		</section>
		<section prefix="C">Any person who purchases gasoline, aviation gasoline, diesel fuel (including dyed diesel fuel), blended fuel, or heating oil upon which the fee imposed by this article has been paid shall be entitled to a refund for the amount of the fee paid if such person subsequently transports and delivers such fuel to another state, district or country for sale or use outside the Commonwealth. The application for refund shall be accompanied by a paid ticket or invoice covering the sales of such fuel and shall be filed with the Commissioner of the Department of Motor Vehicles within one year of the date of payment of the fee for which the refund is claimed. A refund shall not be granted pursuant to this article on any fuel which is transported and delivered outside the Commonwealth in the fuel supply tank of a highway vehicle or aircraft.
		</section>
		<section prefix="D">To maintain the Fund at an appropriate operating level, the Commissioner of the Department of Motor Vehicles shall increase the fee to three-fifths of one cent when notified by the Comptroller that the Fund has been or is likely in the near future to be reduced below three million dollars, exclusive of fees collected pursuant to § 62.1-44.34:21, and he shall reinstitute the one-fifth of one cent fee when the Comptroller notifies him that the Fund has been restored to twelve million dollars exclusive of fees collected pursuant to § 62.1-44.34:21.
		</section>
		<section prefix="E">The Comptroller shall report to the Commissioner quarterly regarding the Fund expenditures and Fund total for the preceding quarter.
		</section>
		<section prefix="F">Revenues from such fees, less refunds and administrative expenses, shall be deposited in the Fund and used for the purposes set forth in this article.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>1989, c. 627; 1992, c. 819; 1993, c. 422; 1995, c. 664; 1996, c. 737; 1998, c. 87; 1999, cc. 119, 124; 2000, cc. 729, 758.</history>
</law>
