<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="2.5" level="3">Chesapeake Bay Preservation Act</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.15:69</section_number>
	<catch_line>Powers and duties of the Board</catch_line>
	<text>
		The Board is responsible for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this article and is authorized to:
		<section prefix="1">Provide land use and development and water quality protection information and assistance to the various levels of local, regional, and state government within the Commonwealth.
		</section>
		<section prefix="2">Consult, advise, and coordinate with the Governor, the Secretary, the General Assembly, other state agencies, regional agencies, local governments, and federal agencies for the purpose of implementing this article.
		</section>
		<section prefix="3">Provide financial and technical assistance and advice to local governments and to regional and state agencies concerning aspects of land use and development and water quality protection pursuant to this article.
		</section>
		<section prefix="4">Promulgate regulations pursuant to the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.).
		</section>
		<section prefix="5">Develop, promulgate, and keep current the criteria required by § 62.1-44.15:72.
		</section>
		<section prefix="6">Provide technical assistance and advice or other aid for the development, adoption, and implementation of local comprehensive plans, zoning ordinances, subdivision ordinances, and other land use and development and water quality protection measures utilizing criteria established by the Board to carry out the provisions of this article.
		</section>
		<section prefix="7">Develop procedures for use by local governments to designate Chesapeake Bay Preservation Areas in accordance with the criteria developed pursuant to § 62.1-44.15:72.
		</section>
		<section prefix="8">Ensure that local government comprehensive plans, zoning ordinances, and subdivision ordinances are in accordance with the provisions of this article. Determination of compliance shall be in accordance with the provisions of the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.).
		</section>
		<section prefix="9">Make application for federal funds that may become available under federal acts and to transmit such funds when applicable to any appropriate person.
		</section>
		<section prefix="10">Take administrative and legal actions pursuant to subdivision (19) of § 62.1-44.15 to ensure compliance by counties, cities, and towns with the provisions of this article including the proper enforcement and implementation of, and continual compliance with, this article.
		</section>
		<section prefix="11">Perform such other duties and responsibilities related to the use and development of land and the protection of water quality as the Secretary may assign.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>1988, cc. 608, 891, § 10.1-2103; 1997, c. 266; 2013, cc. 756, 793; 2016, cc. 68, 758.</history>
</law>
