<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="2" level="3">Control Board Generally</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.15:1</section_number>
	<catch_line>Limitation on power to require construction of sewerage systems or sewage or other waste treatment works; ammonia criteria</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">Nothing contained in this chapter shall be construed to empower the Board to require the Commonwealth, or any political subdivision thereof, or any authority created under the provisions of § 15.2-5102 or §§ 15.2-5152 through 15.2-5158, to construct any sewerage system, sewage treatment works, or water treatment plant waste treatment works or system necessary to (i) upgrade the present level of treatment in existing systems or works to abate existing pollution of state waters or (ii) expand a system or works to accommodate additional growth, unless the Board shall have previously committed itself to provide financial assistance from federal and state funds equal to the maximum amount provided for under § 8 or other applicable sections of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act, P.L. 84-660, as amended, or unless the Commonwealth or political subdivision or authority voluntarily agrees, or is directed by the Board with the concurrence of the Governor, to proceed with such construction, subject to reimbursement under § 8 or other applicable sections of such federal act.
			The foregoing restriction shall not apply to those cases where existing sewerage systems or sewage or other waste treatment works cease to perform in accordance with their approved certificate requirements.
		</section>
		<section prefix="B">Nothing contained in this chapter shall be construed to empower the Board to require the Commonwealth, or any political subdivision thereof, to upgrade the level of treatment in any works to a level more stringent than that required by applicable provisions of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act, P.L. 84-660, as amended.
		</section>
		<section prefix="C">Nothing contained in this chapter shall be construed to empower the Board to adopt the 2013 proposed Aquatic Life Ambient Water Quality Criteria for Ammonia of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency unless the Board includes in such adoption a phased implementation program consistent with the federal Clean Water Act (33 U.S.C. § 1251 et seq.) that includes (i) consideration of the relative priority of ammonia criteria and other water quality and water infrastructure needs of the local community, (ii) mechanisms to coordinate implementation timing with grant funding mechanisms pursuant to § 10.1-2131 and other treatment facility expansion and upgrade plans, (iii) appropriate long-term compliance schedules for facilities or classes of facilities utilizing multiple permit cycles, and (iv) appropriate mechanisms to address affordability limitations and financial hardship situations remaining notwithstanding the other elements of the phased implementation program.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>1971, Ex. Sess., cc. 197, 245; 1973, c. 179; 1975, c. 279; 1981, c. 262; 2018, cc. 510, 511.</history>
</law>
