<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="4" level="3">Regulation of Sewage Discharges</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.19:3.5</section_number>
	<catch_line>Attendance by licensed operator</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">Every sewage treatment works owner shall employ or contract an operator who holds a current wastewater operator license, issued in accordance with Chapter 23 (§ 54.1-2300 et seq.) of Title 54.1, of the appropriate class for the type of facility, as determined by the Department, or higher class at the owner's option. If the position of the licensed operator of the appropriate class is unexpectedly vacated due to death, extended illness, firing for cause, resignation, or similar cause, the treatment works owner shall notify the Department promptly and in accordance with any specific timeframe directed by the Department. The Department shall temporarily waive the licensed operator requirement for the interim, provided the owner (i) informs the Department in writing of its designation of another licensed operator or professional engineer responsible for interim operations within five days of the vacancy, (ii) informs the Department in writing within 10 days of the vacancy arising of its plan to hire a replacement licensed operator of the appropriate class as soon as practicable, (iii) implements the hiring plan diligently, and (iv) provides a monthly report to the Department on the implementation and progress of such hiring plan. The Department may revoke the temporary waiver if the Department finds that continued operation pursuant to the waiver presents a public health or water quality threat due to statutory, regulatory, or permit violations.
		</section>
		<section prefix="B">Where the facility is equipped with adequate technological capability, the Department shall credit remote monitoring of the facility by a licensed operator of the appropriate class as operator attendance toward recommended licensed operator attendance hours, provided that the owner submits and the Department approves a remote monitoring plan demonstrating that the facility possesses sufficient technology for the remote operator to adequately monitor the facility and manage onsite operators with a lower license class, mechanics, or other staff to operate the facility under the remote operator's direct supervision. In determining whether to approve a remote monitoring plan for multiple facilities, the Department may consider the number of facilities the remote operator is monitoring simultaneously, whether the multiple facilities being monitored remotely are under common ownership, whether the remote operator is employed by the owner of the multiple facilities, and whether occasional in-person attendance is provided, among other factors. The Department may cease crediting remote monitoring if the Department finds that continued operation pursuant to the remote monitoring plan presents a public health or water quality threat due to statutory, regulatory, or permit violations. The Department shall not credit remote monitoring by an operator without the appropriate license class who is operating the waterworks or treatment facility pursuant to a temporary waiver issued under subsection A.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>2024, c. 178.</history>
</law>
