<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="13" level="3">Per- and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.34:33</section_number>
	<catch_line>PFAS Expert Advisory Committee; report</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">The Department, in consultation with VDH, shall establish the PFAS Expert Advisory Committee to assist the Department and VDH in identifying (i) PFAS sources through PFAS assessments and associated monitoring and reporting, (ii) public and private lab testing capacity issues, and (iii) options for reducing PFAS in source waters causing exceedances of PFAS MCLs.
		</section>
		<section prefix="B">Members of the Committee shall be appointed by the Director and shall include representatives of public drinking water and wastewater system owners, representatives of public health organizations, potential PFAS source categories, and conservation organizations with expertise in water treatment, water science, or PFAS chemistry, and other experts as determined by the Department. Members of the Committee shall receive no compensation for their service and shall not be entitled to reimbursement for expenses incurred in the performance of their duties.
		</section>
		<section prefix="C">The Department shall convene the Committee at least two times per calendar year through June 30, 2027, and thereafter as the Department deems appropriate.
		</section>
		<section prefix="D">The Department shall report annually by October 1 on its activities related to PFAS assessments, including the self-reporting process pursuant to § 62.1-44.34:31 and the discharge monitoring process pursuant to § 62.1-44.34:32, and on the activities of the Committee to the Governor and the General Assembly.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>2024, cc. 316, 343.</history>
</law>
