<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="2" level="3">Control Board Generally</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.15:3</section_number>
	<catch_line>When application for permit considered complete</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">No application submitted to the Board for a new individual Virginia Pollutant Discharge Elimination permit authorizing a new discharge of sewage, industrial wastes, or other wastes shall be considered complete unless it contains notification from the county, city, or town in which the discharge is to take place that the location and operation of the discharging facility are consistent with applicable ordinances adopted pursuant to Chapter 22 (§ 15.2-2200 et seq.) of Title 15.2. The county, city, or town shall inform in writing the applicant and the Board of the discharging facility's compliance or noncompliance not more than thirty days from receipt by the chief administrative officer, or his agent, of a request from the applicant. Should the county, city, or town fail to provide such written notification within thirty days, the requirement for such notification is waived. The provisions of this subsection shall not apply to any discharge for which a valid certificate had been issued prior to March 10, 2000.</section>
		<section prefix="B">No application for a certificate to discharge sewage into or adjacent to state waters from a privately owned wastewater treatment system serving fifty or more residences shall be considered complete unless the applicant has provided the Executive Director with notification from the State Corporation Commission that the applicant is incorporated in the Commonwealth and is in compliance with all regulations and relevant orders of the State Corporation Commission.</section>
	</text>
	<history>1987, c. 132; 1990, c. 14; 1993, c. 606; 1994, cc. 262, 549; 1995, c. 256; 2000, cc. 19, 98; 2001, c. 492.</history>
</law>
