<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.2" level="2">Conservation of Water Resources; State Water Control Board</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.43</section_number>
	<catch_line>Additional powers of Board</catch_line>
	<text>
		In addition to other powers conferred by the foregoing sections, the Board shall have the following powers:
		<section prefix="a">To administer all funds available to the Board for carrying out the purposes and duties prescribed in §§ 62.1-44.36 through 62.1-44.43;
		</section>
		<section prefix="b">To disburse funds to any department, commission, board, agency, officer or institution of the Commonwealth, or any political subdivision thereof for carrying out such purposes but in the disbursement of such funds the Board shall have no power to include, require or consider membership or nonmembership in any group, organization or political entity of whatsoever nature, and any formula for such distribution; except to the extent as may be required for qualification for such federal funds as may be involved in such distribution;
		</section>
		<section prefix="c">To apply to any appropriate agency or officer of the United States for participation in or the receipt of aid from federal programs respecting or related to conservation or development of the Commonwealth's water and related land resources;
		</section>
		<section prefix="d">To act either independently or jointly with any department, commission, board, agency, officer or institution of the Commonwealth or any political subdivision thereof in order to carry out the Board's powers and duties;
		</section>
		<section prefix="e">To accept gifts, bequests and any other things to be used for carrying out its purposes, powers and duties.
		</section>
	</text>
	<history>Code 1950, § 10-17.8; 1966, c. 561; 1972, c. 728; 1973, c. 450.</history>
</law>
