<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="2.4" level="3">Erosion and Sediment Control Law for Localities Not Administering a Virginia Erosion and Stormwater Management Program</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.15:64</section_number>
	<catch_line>Stop work orders by Board; civil penalties</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">An aggrieved owner of property sustaining pecuniary damage resulting from a violation of an approved erosion and sediment control plan or required land-disturbance approval, or from the conduct of land-disturbing activities commenced without an approved plan or required land-disturbance approval, may give written notice of the alleged violation to the VESCP authority and to the Board.</section>
		<section prefix="B">If the VESCP authority has not responded to the alleged violation in a manner that causes the violation to cease and abates the damage to the aggrieved owner's property within 30 days following receipt of the notice from the aggrieved owner, the aggrieved owner may request that the Board conduct an investigation and, if necessary, require the violator to stop the alleged violation and abate the damage to his property.</section>
		<section prefix="C">If the Board's investigation of the complaint indicates that (i) the VESCP authority has not responded to the alleged violation as required by the VESCP, (ii) the VESCP authority has not responded to the alleged violation within 30 days from the date of the notice given pursuant to subsection A, and (iii) there is a violation and it is necessary to require the violator to cease the violation as requested by the aggrieved owner, then the Board shall give written notice to the VESCP authority that the Board intends to issue an order pursuant to subsection D.</section>
		<section prefix="D">If the VESCP authority has not instituted action to stop the violation and abate the damage to the aggrieved owner's property within 10 days following receipt of the notice from the Board, the Board is authorized to issue an order requiring the owner, person responsible for carrying out an approved erosion and sediment control plan, or person conducting the land-disturbing activities without an approved plan or required land-disturbance approval to cease all land-disturbing activities until the violation of the plan has ceased or an approved plan and required land-disturbance approval are obtained, as appropriate, and specified corrective measures have been completed. The Board also may immediately initiate a program review of the VESCP.</section>
		<section prefix="E">Such orders are to be issued in accordance with the procedures of the Administrative Process Act (§ 2.2-4000 et seq.), and they shall become effective upon service on the person by mailing with confirmation of delivery, sent to his address specified in the land records of the locality, or by personal delivery by an agent of the Board. Any subsequent identical mail or notice that is sent by the Board may be sent by regular mail. However, if the Board finds that any such violation is grossly affecting or presents an imminent and substantial danger of causing harmful erosion of lands or sediment deposition in waters within the watersheds of the Commonwealth, it may issue, without advance notice or hearing, an emergency order directing such person to cease all land-disturbing activities on the site immediately and shall provide an opportunity for a hearing, after reasonable notice as to the time and place thereof, to such person, to affirm, modify, amend, or cancel such emergency order.</section>
		<section prefix="F">If a person who has been issued an order or emergency order is not complying with the terms thereof, the Board may institute a proceeding in the appropriate circuit court for an injunction, mandamus, or other appropriate remedy compelling the person to comply with such order.</section>
		<section prefix="G">Any person violating or failing, neglecting, or refusing to obey any injunction, mandamus, or other remedy obtained pursuant to subsection G shall be subject, in the discretion of the court, to a civil penalty not to exceed $2,000 for each violation. Any civil penalties assessed by a court shall be paid into the state treasury and deposited by the State Treasurer into the Stormwater Local Assistance Fund (§ 62.1-44.15:29.1).</section>
	</text>
	<history>1993, c. 925, § 10.1-569.1; 2012, cc. 785, 819; 2013, cc. 756, 793; 2016, cc. 68, 758.</history>
</law>
