<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="4" level="3">Regulation of Sewage Discharges</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.19</section_number>
	<catch_line>Approval of sewerage systems and sewage treatment works</catch_line>
	<text>
		<section prefix="A">Before any owner may erect, construct, open, expand or operate a sewerage system or sewage treatment works which will have a potential discharge or actual discharge to state waters, such owner shall file with the Board an application for a certificate in scope and detail satisfactory to the Board.</section>
		<section prefix="B">If the application involves a system or works from which there is or is to be a discharge to state waters, the application shall be given public notice by publication once a week for two successive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the county or city where the certificate is applied for or by such other means as the Board may prescribe. Before issuing the certificate, the Board shall consult with and give consideration to the written recommendations of the State Department of Health pertaining to the protection of public health. Upon completion of advertising, the Board shall determine if the application is complete, and if so, shall act upon it within 21 days of such determination. The Board shall approve such application if it determines that minimum treatment requirements will be met and that the discharge will not result in violations of water quality standards. If the Board disapproves the application, it shall state what modifications or changes, if any, will be required for approval.</section>
		<section prefix="C">After the certificate has been issued or amended by the Board, the owner shall acquire from the Department of Environmental Quality (i) authorization to construct the systems or works for which the Board has issued a discharge certificate and (ii) upon completion of construction, authorization to operate the sewerage system or sewage treatment works. These authorizations shall be obtained in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Board.</section>
		<section prefix="D">Any owner operating under a valid certificate issued by the Board who fails to meet water quality standards established by the Board solely as a result of a change in water quality standards or in the law shall provide the necessary facilities approved by the Department of Environmental Quality, in accordance with the provisions of subsection C of this section, within a reasonable time to meet such new requirements. The Board may amend such certificate, or revoke it and issue a new one to reflect such facilities after proper hearing, with at least 30 days' notice to the owner of the time, place and purpose thereof. If such revocation or amendment of a certificate is mutually agreeable to the Board and the owner involved, the hearing and notice may be dispensed with.</section>
		<section prefix="E">The Board shall revoke the certificate in case of a failure to comply with all such requirements and may issue a special order under subdivisions (8a), (8b), and (8c) of § 62.1-44.15.</section>
	</text>
	<history>Code 1950, § 62.1-33; 1968, c. 659; 1970, c. 638; 1976, c. 661; 1991, c. 194; 2003, c. 614.</history>
</law>
