<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>
	<structure>
		<unit label="title" identifier="62.1" level="1">Waters of the State, Ports and Harbors</unit>
		<unit label="chapter" identifier="3.1" level="2">State Water Control Law</unit>
		<unit label="article" identifier="13" level="3">Per- and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances</unit>
	</structure>
	<section_number>62.1-44.34:29</section_number>
	<catch_line>Definitions</catch_line>
	<text>
		As used in this article, unless the context requires a different meaning:
		"Committee" means the PFAS Expert Advisory Committee established in § 62.1-44.34:33.
		"EPA" means the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.
		"HFPO-DA" means hexafluoropropylene oxide dimer acid.
		"PFAS" means per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, which are any fluorinated substances that contain at least one fully fluorinated methyl or methylene carbon atom and any precursors of such substances. "PFAS" includes HFPO-DA, PFBS, PFHxS, PFNA, PFOA, and PFOS.
		"PFAS maximum contaminant level" or "PFAS MCL" means any maximum contaminant level for any PFAS chemical or mixture of PFAS chemicals (i) established by the EPA as a national primary drinking water regulation or (ii) for the interim period of time between the EPA's proposal and final agency action for adopting a national primary drinking water regulation, the EPA's proposed level, provided that the EPA's proposed level may be used only for nonregulatory purposes of self-reporting of manufacturing or use, monitoring, and PFAS assessments as provided in this article.
		"PFBS" means perfluorobutane sulfonate.
		"PFHxS" means perfluorohexane sulfonate.
		"PFNA" means perfluorononanoic acid.
		"PFOA" means perfluorooctanoic acid.
		"PFOS" means perfluorooctane sulfonate.
		"Public water system" means a system that provides piped water for human consumption and (i) serves at least 15 service connections used by year-round residents or regularly serves at least 25 year-round residents or (ii) regularly serves at least 25 of the same persons over six months of the year.
		"VDH" means the Virginia Department of Health.
		"VPDES" means the Virginia Pollutant Discharge Elimination System.
	</text>
	<history>2024, cc. 316, 343.</history>
</law>
